Josef Heidegger

+43 699 1967 5868 josef.heidegger@outlook.at

As a seasoned software engineering leader with over a decade of industry experience, I have honed my skills in mentoring teams towards sustainable success and have a track record of improving engineering practices. My success in leading and scaling a senior engineering team at a start-up gave me invaluable experience, which I have built upon at a rapidly growing enterprise in the renewables sector. Here, I have driven strategic cross department change initiatives about software delivery/release engineering and have used lateral leadership to influence organizational practices and communications.

I am curious, grounded, and visionary and strive to be a decent human being in all aspects of my life.

Work Experience

<u>Fronius International GmbH</u> Manager of Process, Methods & Tools Thalheim bei Wels, Austria HSE, RnD, BU Solar Energy Jun 2021 – Present

Leader and line manager of 2 teams (15 ppl, distributed). Responsibilities include team growth, deliveries, budget, appraisals, and technical direction.

- Grew the *DevOps Platforms* team from 2 to 6 developers and established a clear mission to improve resilience and ownership
- Introduced better engineering practices that improved quality and enable us for decentralized operations
- Established nightly build integrations and bi-weekly alpha deliveries for teams using our platforms that reduced their cycle time by more than 50%
- Influenced the agile mindset of our organization by shaping an *Agile Coaching* team out of scrum masters (that coach >15 distributed teams and ~200 engineers)
- Co-founded a Community of Practice around DevOps and software delivery to reduce redundancies through improved cross department communications
- Successfully used platforms like town hall meetings and internal developer summits to **form alliances** via presentations about our initiatives in front of 100-200 employees

EUVIC Software GmbH

Teamlead Software Development

May 2020 - May 2021

Vienna, Austria

Development Department

Line manager of a team of 10 developers and responsible for modernizing the development and delivery methods as the company was transitioning from a project to a product business model

- Restructured the development team for focus and impact by forming 'delivery teams' around products, introducing elements of Scrum, and hiring two senior developers and one tester
- Introduced practices like CI/CD, code reviews, automated testing, and coached developers to take ownership of the engineering quality resulting in significantly fewer defects and time spent on feedback cycles (~4x)
- Improved the security of the product-platform by managing an external security review/pen-test and overseeing the implementation of the countermeasures for the vulnerabilities
- Met important deadlines for a crucial project via monitoring velocity data and estimating delivery times

Tablet Solutions GmbH

Development Lead

Nov 2016 - Mar 2020

Vienna, Austria

(start-up)

Development lead for the team building the cloud-based workforce management solution <u>workheld.com</u>, responsible for the team, development process and delivery of projects and features

- Grew the development team from 2 to 6 and established a hiring process
- Built out practices like CI/CD, automated testing, code reviews, release toggles, logging, and alerting that enabled automated bi-weekly releases and fast response times to defects
- Sped up critical user interactions ~200x by redesigning the data synchronization flow
- Championed a product customization strategy that was essential for scaling the business model

Tablet Solutions GmbH

Senior Developer, Web & Mobile

Aug 2016 - Oct 2016

Vienna, Austria

(start-up)

Contributing to the mobile and web apps of the 'Industry 4.0' platform workheld.com

- Successfully finished the MVP version of the product on time to extend our runway
- Began as one of the first two engineers and was promoted to Lead Developer after three months

The diamond dogs:group/Emakina CEE Software Developer

Jan 2011 - Jul 2016

Vienna

Development Department

IC for various projects in one of Austria's biggest digital agencies – mostly web/full-stack and mobile – and comaintainer of the company's CI/CD toolchain

Eurofunk Kappacher GmbH

Software Developer Intern

Summer 2010

St. Johann im Pongau, Austria

Development Department

Successfully designed and implemented a camera control interface for airport security of major German airports

Skills

People & Leadership 1-1s, coaching, mentoring, hiring, interviews, leading distributed teams, career

frameworks, team alignment, OKRs, Team Topologies, rapid growth companies

Engineering Practices DevOps, CI/CD, DDD, BDD, OOP, SOA, RESTful, API Design, Trunk Based Development,

Feature Toggles, DORA metrics, cloud native, containers, Kubernetes

Product Development Agile, Scrum, Kanban, SAFe, SaaS products, release management, requirements

engineering, configuration management

Soft Skills Calm personality, empathic, approachable, sense of humor, visionary

Languages

German Native (C2)
English Proficient (C1)
French Basic (A1)

Education and Certifications

• Certified SAFe® 5 Agilist, Scaled Agile, Inc.

2021

• Certified Scrum Master, Agile Alliance

2018

• **Software Engineering**, University of Applied Sciences Upper Austria, Hagenberg (no degree)

2006 - 2010

BG/BRG Gmunden

1997 - 2005

Personal

Besides spending time with my family, I like to read about technology, leadership, and history. I also get myself excited over team-sports and try to find new personal challenges with mountain biking. I prefer to be outside for all of those activities.